{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This state’s Pingree Associates established America’s largest conservation easement around its Allagash River in 2001. This state’s eastern boundary is partially formed by the St. Croix River, which was surveyed as part of Jay’s Treaty. One country hid the Mitchell Map during a dispute over this state’s northern border, which was established along the St. John’s River. The Aroostook War was fought between New Brunswick and, for ten points, what state with capital Augusta?",
      "answer": "Maine"
    },
    {
      "question": "With his brother Manuel, this man set up a “wet line” to prevent immigration and campaigned against the bracero program. He joined forces with the Filipino-dominated AWOC in a campaign where longshoremen refused to load grapes from Delano, California. With Dolores Huerta, he co-founded an organization whose slogan was “Si, se puede,” [pway-day] or “Yes we can.” The United Farm Workers were led by, for ten points, what Mexican-American labor activist?",
      "answer": "Cesar Estrada Chavez"
    },
    {
      "question": "One supporter of these people launched the failed Atterbury Plot. An uprising of these people is the subject of the song “Johnny Cope.” These people launched the failed “Forty-Five” uprising which was defeated at the Battle of Culloden. These people believed in the legitimacy of Bonnie Prince Charlie to the throne. For ten points, name these people who claimed that the House of Stuart were the legitimate heirs to the British throne.",
      "answer": "Jacobites"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to his career as a politician, this man owned a firefighting business notorious for letting properties burn down so that this man could buy the land. He punished Mummius during the Third Servile War by renewing the practice of decimation. After the Battle of Carrhae, the Parthians killed this man by pouring molten gold down his throat. For ten points, name this legendarily rich Roman leader, a member of the First Triumvirate with Julius Caesar and Pompey the Great.",
      "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Harry Trask captured three iconic photographs of Jock Semple accosting Katherine Switzer during one of these events, which Switzer entered under her initials. The testimony of John Faulkner helped discover Rosie Ruiz’s fraudulent claims about one of these sporting events. In 2012, one of these events was canceled in the aftermath of Superstorm Sandy. The traditional last event of the Summer Olympics is, for ten points, what sporting event, which was the site of a 2013 bombing in Boston?",
      "answer": "marathon"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work ends by saying “instead of gazing at each other with suspicious or doubtful curiosity, let each of us hold out [...] the hearty hand of friendship,” before calling “Let the names of Whig and Tory be extinct.” Benajmin Rush edited this work, whose final section calculates the value of the British navy, noting America’s natural resources give it the potential to rival it. The absurdity of an island ruling over a continent is noted by, for ten points, what 1776 pro-revolution pamphlet by Thomas Paine?",
      "answer": "Common Sense"
    },
    {
      "question": "War broke out between this country and its eastern neighbour after the death of Inspector Grosgurin. Guy Tachard was sent by Louis XIV to become ambassador of this modern day country. This non- European country underwent a 1688 revolution, which overthrew the pro-foreign King Narai. This modern day country, once home to the Ayutthaya Kingdom, is now led by the Chakri Dynasty’s King Rama IX. For ten points, name this country formerly known as Siam, whose capital is Bangkok.",
      "answer": "Thailand"
    },
    {
      "question": "The body of Ulric Dahlgren was discovered in this city with an apparent order to burn it down. Dozens of POWs escaped this city in the Libby prison break. Joseph Reid Anderson protected this city’s Tredegar Iron Works from arson; that site is now home to a controversial statue of Tad and Abraham Lincoln, who toured this city after that “Evacuation Fire.” Shortly after the fall of Petersburg, Jefferson Davis fled from, for ten points, what Virginia city, the capital of the Confederacy?",
      "answer": "Richmond"
    },
    {
      "question": "The execution of Mishaal, a member of this family, is depicted in the documentary Death of a Princess. The Battle of Sabila was a victory for one ruler from this house, leading to the defeat of the Ikhwan revolt. The economic well-being of this house is highly linked to the success of ARAMCO. The current head of this family, which supports the Wahhabi mission, became King in January 2015 after the death of his brother, Abdullah, in Riyadh. For ten points, name this Arab royal family led by King Salman, that rules over Saudi Arabia.",
      "answer": "House of Saud"
    },
    {
      "question": "Baron d’Holbach’s The System of Nature refuted this concept, which was advocated for in a discussion of infinite gains and avoiding infinite losses that appeared in Pens´ees [pawn-say]. Maximilian Robespierre led a group that supported this concept but believed the subject was passive: the Cult of the Supreme Being. Blaise Pascal wagered in favor of, for ten points, what theological concept concerning the presence of higher beings, which is opposed by atheists?",
      "answer": "existence of gods ”"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The twelve Jyotirlinga [j’yoh-teer-LINGA] shrines dedicated to this god include one at Somnath and the Rameswaram temple, which includes a body of water named for Agni, a cognate of this modern god. Statues of this god wear five serpents and hold a trident in one of their four arms. With Parvati, this god is the father of Ganesha. For ten points, name this Hindu destruction god who forms the Trimurti with Brahma and Vishnu.",
        "answer": "Shiva or Siva"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Like Agni, Rudra is historically closely related to Shiva; this monkey king from the Ramayana is sometimes considered an avatar of Rudra.",
        "answer": "Hanuman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s crew was saved from scurvy by treebark tea, a solution provided by Domagaya from the Stadacona village; The next spring, he kidnapped Domagaya and Donnacona to bring back to Europe. This man names a bridge that reaches Saint Helen’s Island as it connects Longueuil [long-ay] and Montreal Island. This man’s failure to find a Northwest Passage resulted in claims on the Saint Lawrence River. For ten points, name this explorer who, in the 1530s, claimed Canada for France.",
        "answer": "Jacques Cartier"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In lieu of a Northwest Passage through the continent, this Norwegian explorer completed a journey through the Arctic that started in 1903. He disappeared on a rescue mission in 1928.",
        "answer": "Roald Amundsen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One politician from this country, Robert Grimm, attempted to negotiate peace between Germany and Russia, causing an affair that led to the resignation of this country’s councilor Arthur Hoffmann. This country’s actions during World War II were the subject of the Bergier Commission. Jean-Henri Durant was so shocked at the devastation from the Battle of Solferino that he founded the Red Cross in this country, which is divided into 26 cantons. For ten points, name this neutral country in the Alps whose cities include Zurich and Geneva.",
        "answer": "Switzerland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Switzerland was rather slow in legalizing this action, which it finally did in 1971. New Zealand was the first country to legalize this action in 1893.",
        "answer": [
          "women’s suffrage",
          "descriptions of allowing women to vote"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man hosted a fundraiser for the Black Panthers that Tom Wolfe described as “radical chic.” His third symphony was dedicated to the memory of JFK and was based on the Jewish prayer for the dead. Another piece by this composer of the Kaddish Symphony included a “rumble” between the Sharks and Jets and songs such as “Gee, Officer Krupke” and “America”. For ten points, what conductor of the New York Philharmonic wrote the music for West Side Story?",
        "answer": "Leonard Bernstein"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leonard Bernstein also wrote the music for what operetta, based on a Voltaire work that parodied Gottfried Liebniz as Dr. Pangloss?",
        "answer": "Candide"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Pope Alexander II sent papal standards to the victor of this battle in an attempt to expand Catholic power. Many retreating troops from the losing side of this battle fell into the Evil Ditch, or the “Malfosse.” In this battle, which was preceded by an engagement at Fulford, the losing side’s huscarls could not prevent their king from being shot in the eye. The English formed a shield wall in this battle, fought three weeks after Harald Hardrada was killed at Stamford Bridge. For ten points, name this 1066 victory for William the Conqueror over Harold Godwinson.",
        "answer": "Battle of Hastings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The heirless death of this English king, a son of Aethelred the Unready, led to the succession crisis that ended with William’s victory at Hastings.",
        "answer": "Edward the Confessor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this man gave up alcohol, he allegedly received divine aid in his fight against Rana Sanga. In his early career, this man saw his rival Mohammed Shaybani Khan capture Ferghana and Samarkand from him, though he was able to seize Kabul. Alam Khan and Dawlat Khan encouraged this descendant of Genghis Khan to launch one invasion that culminated in the defeat of Ibrahim Lodi at the battle of Panipat. For ten points, name this father of Humayun and founder of the Mughal Dynasty.",
        "answer": "Babur"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Babur was the great-great-great-grandson of this ruler who sieged the Knights Hospitallers at Smyrna in 1402.",
        "answer": "Timur the Lame or Tamerlane"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Amendments to this treaty were included in the Protocol of Queretaro, and it was preceded by a cessation of hostilities known as the Capitulation of Cahuenga. The chief negotiator of this treaty was Nicholas Trist. One party to this treaty paid the other 15 million dollars in exchange for land that included Alta California, and it established the Rio Grande as the undisputed southern border of Texas. For ten points, name this 1848 treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What proposal, named after its Pennsylvania sponsor, attempted to ban slavery in territory acquired by America in the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo?",
        "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Edward Savage painted a portrait of this man’s family with an enslaved Christopher Sheels in the background. The “Apotheosis” of this man was painted by Constantino Brumidi in the rotunda of the U.S. Capitol Building. Other depictions of this man include the Lansdowne Portrait and the unfinished Athenaeum [uh-THEE-nee-um]. For ten points, name this politician, depicted by Gilbert Stuart on the one-dollar bill.",
        "answer": "George Washington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A replica of the Landsdowne Portrait can be found in this largest room in the White House, used for banquets and ceremonies. Omar Gonzalez was tackled after reaching this room during his White House break-in.",
        "answer": "East Room"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Spanish-American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Future U.S. President who led the Rough Riders in Cuba.",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "American battleship sunk in Havana harbor, leading to the declaration of war.",
          "answer": "USS Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "1898 treaty that ended the war.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacific island, still a US territory with capital Hagatna, ceded by Spain after the war.",
          "answer": "Guam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodore who led the American fleet to victory at Manila Bay.",
          "answer": "George Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper published by William Randolph Hearst, a rival of Pulitzer’s New York World, which “furnished the war” via yellow journalism.",
          "answer": "New York Journal"
        },
        {
          "question": "First President of the Philippines, who originally fought with the Americans against the Spanish, but was captured in 1901 during the Philippine-American War.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorado senator whose namesake amendment, passed prior to the war, required the U.S. to help Cuba gain independence, then leave without annexing it.",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Teller",
            "Teller Amendment"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Famous Canadians",
      "prompt": "Which Canadian...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Has hosted Jeopardy! for over 30 years?",
          "answer": "Alex Trebek"
        },
        {
          "question": "Invented numerous hearing aid devices, as well as the telephone?",
          "answer": "Alexander Graham Bell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took a “long walk in the snow” in 1984, after which he announced plans to retire as Prime Minister?",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Invented basketball at a YMCA in Springfield, Massachusetts?",
          "answer": "James Naismith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discussed wealth discrepancies in post-World War II America in The Affluent Society?",
          "answer": "John Kenneth Galbraith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote “In Flanders Fields” in memory of a fallen friend during World War I?",
          "answer": "John McCrae"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won a Nobel at age 32 for his discovery of insulin?",
          "answer": "Frederick Banting"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commanded the ISS in 2013 and became the first Canadian to walk in space?",
          "answer": "Chris Hadfield"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial Asia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country whose Qing dynasty agreed to the Convention of Peking after European soldiers entered the Forbidden City.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese colony established across the Pearl River Delta from Hong Kong.",
          "answer": "Macao"
        },
        {
          "question": "American Commodore who forced Japan to open its ports with the Treaty of Kanagawa.",
          "answer": "Matthew Calbraith Perry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Policy that resulted from John Hay’s note requesting that trade should be equal between all European powers.",
          "answer": "Open Door Policy"
        },
        {
          "question": "First of the Unequal Treaties, whose singing ended the First Opium War.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Nanking or Nanjing"
        },
        {
          "question": "International alliance formed to aid the Qing during the Boxer Rebellion.",
          "answer": "Eight-Nation Alliance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Fort Zeelandia was established by the Dutch East India Company.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan",
            "Formosa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Iron “devil ship” captained by William Hutcheon Hull that sank the Cambridge and that aided in the capture of Canton during the First Opium War.",
          "answer": "Nemesis"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1919, socialist Victor Berger’s seat in Congress was disqualified under this amendment’s third section. John Bingham reworded one section of this amendment to remove language describing (20 pts)",
        "racial discrimination in favor of broader protection. Its fourth section refused to honor debts made by the Confederacy, and its first section notes that “[no] State shall deprive any person of life, liberty, or property without (10 pts)",
        "due process of law.” The Equal Protection clause is contained in, for ten points, what Reconstruction amendment that granted “all persons born [...] in the United States” citizenship?"
      ],
      "answer": "14th Amendment"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Works from this dynasty describe Yang Guifei, one of the four beauties. During this dynasty, Emperor Xuangzong and Wang Wei resided in Chang’an before being displaced by rebels. “Departing from (20 pts)",
        "Baidi in the Morning” was written by one author from this dynasty while returning from exile after the An Lushan rebellion. (10 pts)",
        "“Drinking Alone by Moonlight” and “The River Merchant’s Wife” were written by Li Bai during, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty, known as the “golden age” of Chinese poetry, that followed the Sui dynasty?"
      ],
      "answer": "Tang Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Victory Polay Campos founded the MRTA in this country. Jose Bustamante became president of this country with the assistance of the APRA. One president of this country was known as “el Chino” despite being of (20 pts)",
        "Japanese origin. The Tupac Amaru Revolutionary Movement took part in this country’s Internal Conflict. Abimael Guzman led the Shining (10 pts)",
        "Path guerrillas in this country, which fought against the presidency of Alberto Fujimori. For ten points, name this South American country that was home to the Incan civilization."
      ],
      "answer": "Peru"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This song’s final line was sometimes changed in performance to say that Jimmy Carter’s “got the answer.” This song references the Swampers of Muscle Shoals, and features the line “Now Watergate does not bother me, does your conscience bother you?” Written as a response to Neil Young’s (20 pts)",
        "“Southern Man,” its writer claimed that the line “Boo! Boo! Boo!” meant that he did not actually love Governor (10 pts)",
        "George Wallace. For ten points, name this Lynyrd Skynyrd song about a Southern state “where the skies are so blue.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Sweet Home Alabama"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Kahun and the Edwin Smith papyruses were early Egyptian texts related to this discipline, the latter of which may have been written by Djoser’s chancellor Imhotep. Thomas Percival wrote the first text outlining the ethics required in this discipline, which was further advanced in the post-Holocaust (20 pts)",
        "Nuremberg Code. A 1928 discovery by Alexander Fleming revolutionized this discipline, whose practitioners are advised to (10 pts)",
        "“do no harm” by an ancient Greek text. The Hippocratic Oath governs, for ten points, what discipline that seeks to prevent and treat disease?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "medicine",
        "equivalents and descriptions, such as doctoring"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Operation Fortitude North gave the impression that an invasion of this country was imminent. Ahmed Bouchiki was killed in this country by Mossad agents who thought he was a member of Black September. (20 pts)",
        "Oscar II renounced his claim to the throne of this country, leading to Haakon VII becoming king. This country was ruled by the Nasjonal (10 pts)",
        "Samling party during its occupation by Nazi Germany under Prime Minister Vidkun Quisling. For ten points, name this Scandinavian country whose capital is Oslo."
      ],
      "answer": "Norway"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Donald Cunnell wounded this man a week before being killed at Wervik. This man’s cousin Wolfram was placed in charge of Operation Rugen, carried out by the Condor Legion. He served with his brother Lothar in (20 pts)",
        "Jasta [yah-sta] 11. Lanoe Hawker, the so-called “British Boelcke,” was killed by this instigator of “Bloody April,” whose pursuit of a Sopwith Camel ended with his defeat near (10 pts)",
        "Amiens [ah-mee-ehn] in April 1918 by Roy Brown. For ten points, name this leader of the Flying Circus, a distinguished German ace of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "The Red Baron or Manfred von Richthofen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech references a passage from the book of Isaiah, commanding to “let the oppressed go free.” Its speaker warned leaders of newly-freed countries that those who “foolishly sought power by riding the back of the tiger ended up inside,” shortly after stating that he will (20 pts)",
        "“bear any burden” and “oppose any foe.” This speech, which declared that the “torch has been passed to a new generation of Americans,” was preceded by a recitation of “The (10 pts)",
        "Gift Outright”. For ten points, name this speech, in which a newly sworn-in President declared “ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country.”"
      ],
      "answer": "John F. Kennedy’s inaugural address"
    }
  ]
}